Pi Omega Pi; Records ua800.013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Pi Omega Pi, Beta Eta Chapter Records
1942-1986
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Pi Omega Pi. Beta Eta Chapter
ua800.013
1.66 cubic ft.
The Pi Omega Pi Records contain documents pertaining to the National Business Education Teacher Honor Society's Beta Eta chapter at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Royann Blodgett donated all of the materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in April 2003.
Biographical Sketch
Pi Omega Pi is the National Business Education Teacher Honor Society, which has the purpose of promoting scholarship and service in the area of business education. The Society was founded in 1923 at the Northeast Missouri State Teachers College. The University at Albany Beta Eta chapter was chartered in 1942 when the school was named the New York State College for Teachers. Dr. Edward Cooper, professor of business, established the Beta Eta chapter and served as its faculty sponsor for fifteen years. Most of the chapter's activities involved community and social functions, encouraging students in the field of teaching business subjects, as well as contributing to the national organization as a whole.
Scope and Contents
The Pi Omega Pi, Beta Eta Chapter Records include the 1942 charter for the organization, though the bulk of records document the chapter’s activity from the 1960s through the 1980s. This activity is reflected in administrative documents such as meeting minutes and a treasury book, as well as the organization’s social functions which are documented through banquet and initiation programs and scrapbooks. There also are files about a memorial scholarship established to honor Dr. Edward Cooper at the university. Other records in the collection reflect the society at the national level through the inclusion of such items as a national organizational history, newsletters, constitution and brochures.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 is arranged alphabetically while Series 2 is arranged chronologically.
Business education--New York (State); Learned instiutions and societies; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Albany (N.Y.); Scrapbooks; Newsletters; Correspondence; Photographs; Minutes; Programs (documents); UAlbany Student Groups; Pi Omega Pi; Pi Omega Pi--Beta Eta Chapter (State University of New York at Albany); State University of New York at Albany
- Administrative, 1942; 1954; 1960-1986; Undated; 1; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  In addition to containing the 1942 Charter for the Beta Eta Chapter, this series also includes documents for governance, financial information and meeting minutes. There are files about the Dr. Edward Cooper scholarship, newsletters and general correspondence as well as materials from social functions, such as an initiation sign-in book and initiation programs.
  - Banquet and Initiation Programs, 1964-1965; 1974-1975; 1977-1979; 1981-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 1)
  - Biennial Delegates Convention Photograph, 1972 (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
  - Chapter Evaluation Packet, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 2)
  - Charter, 1942 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 3)
  - Edward L. Cooper Scholarship, 1963; 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 4)
  - Edward L. Cooper Faculty Sponsors, 1962-1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 5)
  - Financials, 1954; 1969-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1977; 1979; 1981; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 7)
  - History, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 8)
  - Initation Sign-In Book, 1980-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 9)
  - Member Roster, 1982-1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 10)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1960-1969 April (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 11)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1969 November-1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 12)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 13)
  - National Chapter Rankings, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 14)
  - National Constitution (Revised), 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 15)
  - National Society Brochure, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1974; 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 17)
- Scrapbooks, 1953-1983; 2; 0.74 cubic ft.
  This series consists of eight scrapbooks, covering select years from 1953 to 1983, the late 1970s and early 1980s most strongly represented. Therefore the overall dates are not inclusive. Most scrapbooks contain photographs, though some include mixed materials and paper ephemera.
  - Scrapbook, 1953-1954 (Oversized 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Oversized 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1967 (Oversized 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1975-1976 (Oversized 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1976-1977 (Oversized 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1980 (Oversized 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1981-1982 (Oversized 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1983 (Oversized 3)